Guide to the Sir William Lee Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Sir William Lee family papers
1588-1814
1710-1754
OSB MSS 52
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
17.29
(28 boxes)
The papers, most of which date from the lifetime of Sir William Lee, consist of personal and official correspondence, notes, memoranda, household accounts and financial papers, records of court cases, and other documents. Family correspondents include Lee's brothers Sir George and Thomas Lee; his brother-in-law, William Melmoth, and his son William. William's letters describe student life at Wadham College, Oxford and Clare College, Cambridge. Subsequent letters detail William's Grand Tour through continental Europe, with sojourns in Paris; several cities in Italy, including Rome; and at the imperial court of Austria-Hungary. Other correspondents include Scroop Egerton, the Duke of Bridgewater; Sir Roger Drake; and Lord Hardwicke. Hardwicke's letters concern patronage, the Marriage Act of 1753, and the trials of the Jacobite rebels, including Lords Kilmarnock, Cromarty and Balmerino. Other subjects represented in Lee's correspondence includecounty politics and elections and local legal matters; news of Parliament and current events, including the Jacobite Rebellion and the War of the Austrian Succession; and medical remedies and receipts. There are also letters from prisoners asking for pardons or commutations, and from tenants concerning estate matters.
Lee, William, Sir, 1688-1754
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased by James Marshall Osborn from Sotheby's, 8 March 1939 (Hartwell sale); gift of James Marshall Osborn, 1967.
Box 22, Fresh Wharf Estate Papers, was purchased from Bernard Quaritch, Ltd. on the James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Fund, 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Sir William Lee, 1688-1754
Sir William Lee was born at Hartwell, Buckinghamshire, England, in 1688, the second son of Sir Thomas Lee of Hartwell, M.P. for Aylesbury. He was admitted to the Middle Temple in 1704, and soon after matriculated at Wadham College, Oxford, but did not take a degree. He was called to the bar in 1710, was appointed Latin secretary to King George I in 1718, and ten years later was named attorney-general to Frederick Prince of Wales. In 1727 he was elected to Parliament for Chipping Wycombe through his family's interest, and served until he was appointed a puisne justice of the King's Bench in 1730.
Lee married Anne Goodwin early in his career, and the couple had one son, William (d. 1778). Anne died in 1729, and in 1733 Lee married Margaret Drake Melmoth, a widow with a fortune of 25,000 pounds. In the same year, Lee's friend and colleague Lord Hardwicke was named Chief Justice. When Hardwicke was further promoted to Lord Chancellor in February 1737, he nominated Lee as his successor. Lee became Chief Justice on June 8th, and was also knighted that day as well.
Lee served as Chief Justice until his death, and was praised for his ability and impartiality as a judge. His court ruled that women who paid parish rates were entitled to vote in elections of parish officers. Lee presided at several of the treason trials of Jacobite rebels held by the special commission at Southwark in 1746. Among his rulings was R. v. Townley, which denied the defendant the right to be treated as a prisoner of war even though he held a commission in the service of the Pretender.
Lady Margaret Lee died in 1752; Sir William Lee died at his residence in Bloomsbury Square, London, after a stroke, on April 8, 1754. He was buried in the church at Hartwell, and left his fortune, including his manor at Totteridge, Hertfordshire, to his son William.
Scope and Contents
The Sir William Lee Family Papers document many aspects of the personal, family, and professional life of the prominent jurist and landowner Sir William Lee and his extended family. They include extensive personal and official correspondence; records of court cases; notes on legal and Parliamentary questions; personal, financial and legal memoranda; household accounts and financial papers; and other family and personal papers.
Series I, Correspondence, includes letters by William Lee (1729-1778) describing his extensive Grand Tour, as well as letters from other Lee relatives and Lord Hardwicke. Other subjects represented in the correspondence include county politics and elections and local legal matters; news of Parliament and current events, including the Jacobite Rebellion and the War of the Austrian Succession.
The remaining series primarily document Lee family financial and legal matters and Lee's service as Chief Justice. Additional documents relating to the Jacobite Rebellion are located in Series III, Political and Governmental Papers. A catalogue of Lee's library, along with many notes by Lee on his wide reading, is located in Series V, Notes on Reading and Other Papers.
Arrangement
Organized into nine series: I. Correspondence, 1724-1797; II. Financial Papers, 1700-1796; III. Political and Governmental Papers, 1700-1770; IV. Personal and Family Papers, 1588-1796; V. Notes on Reading and Other Papers, 1750; VI. Miscellaneous Legal Papers and Documents, 1700-1770; VII. Printed Materials, 1745-1814; VIII. 2002 Addition (02.5.8), 1695-1776; IX. Oversize, 1602-1806.
Administration of estates -- Great Britain; Austrian Succession, War of, 1740-1748; Families -- England -- Domestic relations; Farm tenancy -- Economic aspects -- Great Britain; Grand tours (Education); Jacobite Rebellion, 1745-1746; Landlord and tenant -- Great Britain; Law -- Great Britain; Medicine -- Great Britain; Prisoners -- Great Britain; Private libraries -- England -- Catalogs; Europe -- Description and travel; Great Britain -- History -- 1714-1837; Great Britain -- Politics and government -- 1714-1727; Great Britain -- Politics and government -- 1727-1760; Judges -- Great Britain; Bridgewater, Scroop Egerton, Duke of, 1681-1745; Drake, Roger, Sir; Hardwicke, Philip Yorke, Earl of, 1690-1764; Lee, William, 1729-1778; Lee, William, Sir, 1688-1754; Lee family
- Correspondence, 1724-1797; Series I; 1.67; (4 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Alphabetically arranged. General correspondence files for single letters or letter spans precede files for individual correspondents.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, documents the personal and professional activities of jurist and landowner Sir William Lee. Family correspondents include his brothers Sir George Lee and Thomas Lee and his brother in law William Melmoth.
  There are eleven folders of letters from William Lee (1729-1778) to his father Sir William. The earliest letters describe student life at Wadham College, Oxford and Clare College, Cambridge. Subsequent letters detail William's Grand Tour through continental Europe, with sojourns in Paris; several cities in Italy, including Rome; and at the imperial court of Austria-Hungary.
  Major correspondents include Scroop Egerton, the Duke of Bridgewater; Sir Roger Drake; and Lord Hardwicke. Hardwicke's letters concern patronage, the Marriage Act of 1753, and the trials of the Jacobite rebels, including Lords Kilmarnock, Cromarty and Balmerino.
  Other subjects represented in the correspondence include county politics and elections and local legal matters; news of Parliament and current events, including the Jacobite Rebellion and the War of the Austrian Succession; and medical remedies and receipts. There are also letters from prisoners asking for pardons or commutations, and from tenants concerning estate matters.
  Additional information on the Jacobite Rebellion is found in Series III, Political and Governmental Papers.
  - A-B, 1746-1752, undated (Box 1)
  - Antonie, Richard, 1768-1769 (Box 1)
  - Bickham, Richard, 1793 (Box 1)
  - Bridgewater, Scroop Egerton, 1st Duke of (1681-1745), 1725-1729 (Box 1)
  - Brown, Samuel and Gregory, 1743-1753; 2 (Box 1)
  - Burnett, Thomas, 1745-1750 (Box 1)
  - C, 1738-1769 (Box 1)
  - Calthorpe, Ja., 1736-1739 (Box 1)
  - D, 1746-1789 (Box 1)
  - Davers, M., no year, April 18 (Box 1)
  - De la Touche, William, 1791-1792 (Box 1)
  - Denison, Thomas, 1757 (Box 1)
  - Drake, Roger, 1737-1753 (Box 1)
  - Duncombe, T., 1743-1753 (Box 1)
  - E-F-G, 1735-1753, undated (Box 1)
  - Firebrace, G., 1797 March 7 (Box 1)
  - Fortesque of Credan, John Fortesque Alana, 1st baron (1670-1746), 1745 December (Box 1)
  - Gautier, Joseph, undated (Box 1)
  - George II, King of Great Britain (1683-1760), 1737 (Box 1)
  - Gideon, Samson, 1739-1742 (Box 1)
  - Grigby, Josiah, 1738-1749 (Box 1)
  - Gamutt, Will, 1740 June 16 (Box 1)
  - H-I, 1737-1752 (Box 2)
  - Hardwicke, Philip Yorke, 1st Earl of (1690-1764), 1736-1754; 4 (Box 2)
  - Henley, John, 1742-1747 (Box 2)
  - Holland, Henry Fox, 1st Baron (1705-1774), 1750-1754 (Box 2)
  - Hume-Campbell, Alexander (1708-1756), 1747-1752 (Box 2)
  - Hoden, Robert, 1737-1740 (Box 2)
  - J-K-L, 1739-1769, undated (Box 2)
  - Lee, Sir Thomas, 3rd bart, (1687-1749), 1737-1745 (Box 2)
  - Lee, Thomas, 1768 (Box 2)
  - Lee, Margaret (d. 1752), 1748-1752; 2 (Box 2)
  - Lee, John, 1730-1753; 2 (Box 2)
  - Lee, Sir George (1700-1758), 1741-[1754?] (Box 2)
  - Lee, William (1726-1778), 1739-1753, undated; 7 (Box 2)
  - Lee, William (1726-1778), 1753-1754; 4 (Box 3)
  - Lee, Sir William (1688-1754), 1730-1754; 9 (Box 3)
  - Lee, Sir William, 4th bart. (d. 1749), 1751-1768; 2 (Box 3)
  - Le Neve, Edward, 1746-1747 (Box 3)
  - Liptrott, Bexworth, 1752 November 8 (Box 3)
  - M, 1731-1789, undated (Box 3)
  - Maddox, Isaac, bp. of Worcester (1688-1754), 1740-1752 (Box 3)
  - Marlborough, Sarah Jennings Churchill, Duchess of (1660-1744), 1744 August (Box 3)
  - Melmoth, William, 1745-1750 (Box 3)
  - Moss, Alexander, 1752-1753 (Box 3)
  - N-R, 1741-1759, undated (Box 3)
  - Norfolk, Mary Blount Howard, Duchess of (1702-1773), 1744-1745 (Box 3)
  - Onslow, Arthur, 1737-1751 (Box 3)
  - Owen, Thomas, 1750-1753 (Box 3)
  - Parker, Thomas (1695?-1784), 1740-1749 (Box 4)
  - Perkins, Hutton, 1741-1748 (Box 4)
  - Reynolds, Isaac, 1735-1736 (Box 4)
  - Rooke, Mav, 1791 October (Box 4)
  - Scott, George Lewis (1708-1780), 1751-1752 (Box 4)
  - Schaw, Frederick Bridges, 1752 December (Box 4)
  - S, 1737-1783, undated (Box 4)
  - Sherwin, John, 1750 (Box 4)
  - Skynner, John, 1743-1753 (Box 4)
  - Snow, Robert and Thomas, 1741-1752 (Box 4)
  - Somerset, 1738-1744 (Box 4)
  - Staines, John, 1751-1753 (Box 4)
  - Stanyan, Grace, [1753?] (Box 4)
  - Swale, John, 1748-1752 (Box 4)
  - T-V, 1738-1751 (Box 4)
  - Taafe, Jacob?, 1748-1751 (Box 4)
  - Twinor, John, 1736-1737 (Box 4)
  - Vernon, Anne (Lee) (d. 1742), 1724-1742; 2 (Box 4)
  - Vernon, Edward (b. 1670), 1738-1739 (Box 4)
  - Vernon, George Venables, 1739-1752; 2 (Box 4)
  - W-Z, 1743-1754 (Box 4)
  - Ward, Philip, 1739-1746 (Box 4)
  - Waller, John, 1768-1770; 2 (Box 4)
  - Williams, Hutchins and Judith, 1736-1742 (Box 4)
  - Wilmot, Robert, 1738 June 10 (Box 4)
  - Unidentified, 1750, undated (Box 4)
  - Wrappers, 1740-1752, undated (Box 4)
- Financial Papers, 1700-1796; Series II; 2.9; (5 boxes)
  Arranged in two subseries: Personal Accounts and Court Accounts.
  Series II, Financial Papers, contains accounts, bills and receipts, memoranda, and other financial records. The subseries Personal Accounts documents the finances of Sir William Lee and of his extended family. The papers in Court Accounts record financial data for assize and circuit courts in Norwich and other places.
  - Personal Accounts
    - Personal, 1700-1754, undated; 6 (Box 5)
    - Personal Financial, 1700-1796, undated; 6 (Box 5)
    - Personal Bills and Receipts, 1700-1740; 2 (Box 5)
    - Personal Bills and Receipts, 1741-1796, undated; 5 (Box 6)
    - Account Book with Snow and Co., 1743-1764 (Box 6)
    - Melmoth Account Book, 1717-1740 (Box 6)
    - Melmoth-Lee Account Book, 1730-1739 (Box 6)
    - Household Accounts, 1754-1796 (Box 6)
  - Court Accounts
    - Court Accounts, 1700-1740; 3 (Box 6)
    - Court Accounts, 1741-1754; 12 (Box 7)
    - Court Accounts, 1755-1760 (Box 8)
    - Assize Accounts, 1738-1753; 2 (Box 8)
    - Norwich Circuit Receipts, 1737-1744; 3 (Box 8)
    - Court Procedures, 1700-1754, undated; 7 (Box 9)
    - Lawyers' Bill for Services, 1784 (Box 9)
- Political and Governmental Papers, 1700-1770; Series III; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Documents are arranged by subject and then chronologically.
  Series III contains notes and papers documenting Sir William Lee's political activities and interests.. Many of the papers relate to the Jacobite Rebellion of 1745 and its aftermath. There are also two folders on prison conditions.
  - Elections and Local Government, 1700-1754; 5 (Box 9)
  - Elections and Local Government, undated; 4 (Box 10)
  - Parliamentary and Political, 1734-1745; 2 (Box 10)
  - Parliamentary and Political, 1746-1754; 2 (Box 11)
  - The "45", 1746-1750 (Box 11)
  - Felonies and Violence, 1700-1754, undated; 7 (Box 11)
  - Prison Conditions, 1734-1745, undated; 2 (Box 11)
  - Libel and Censorship, 1736-1770 (Box 11)
- Personal and Family Papers, 1588-1796; Series IV; 1.88; (5 boxes)
  Documents are arranged by subject.
  Series IV, Personal and Family Papers, contains notes, legal documents, accounts, rental books, and other papers roughly sorted by subject. Many may be concerned with investments or holdings of the Lee family.
  - Land, 1588-1754, undated; 11 (Box 12)
  - Debt, 1700-1796, undated; 13 (Box 13)
  - Commercial, 1734-1748, undated; 8 (Box 14)
  - Maritime (including insurance), 1732-1748, undated; 6 (Box 14)
  - Inheritance, 1700-1733; 4 (Box 14)
  - Inheritance, 1734-1796; 13 (Box 15)
  - Inheritance, undated; 5 (Box 16)
- Notes on Reading and Other Papers, 1750, undated; Series V; 0.63; (2 boxes) (Box 16)
  Arranged alphabetically by subject or type of material.
  Series V consists almost entirely of notes in Sir William Lee's hand on various subjects; many appear to be summaries of the contents of books, pamphlets and cases. There are also a notebook containing a catalog of Lee's library and a folder of medicinal recipes in various hands.
  - Catalogue of library, 1750 (Box 17)
  - History and Geography, undated (Box 17)
  - Legal, undated; 4 (Box 17)
  - Literary, undated (Box 17)
  - Medical and Scientific, undated (Box 17)
  - Playing Cards and Architectural Drawing, undated (Box 17)
  - Poetry, undated (Box 17)
  - Political, undated (Box 17)
  - Recipes, undated (Box 17)
  - Religion and Philosophy, undated (Box 17)
  - Religion and Philosophy, undated; 7 (Box 18)
- Miscellaneous Legal Papers and Documents, 1700-1770; Series VI; 0.63; (2 boxes) (Box 18)
  Contents include notes, legal documents including petitions and sentences, and other papers related to legal questions. The folder on "Marriage" primarily concerns the 1753 Marriage Act and its effects on clandestine marriages.
  - Colonial, 1737-1770, undated (Box 19)
  - Ecclesiastical Cases, 1743-1753, undated; 2 (Box 19)
  - Marriage, 1736-1753, undated (Box 19)
  - Military, 1742-1745, undated (Box 19)
  - Social Problems, 1737, undated (Box 19)
  - Miscellaneous and unidentified, 1700-1754, undated; 14 (Box 20)
- Printed Materials, 1745-1814; Series VII; 0.21; (1 box)
  Arranged in no particular order.
  Pamphlets, broadsides, Parliamentary speeches and other ephemeral printed items.
  - Lee Printed, 1745-1814; 18 (Box 21)
- 2002 Addition (02.5.8), 1695-1776; Series VIII; 0.21; (1 box)
  The series contains financial and legal documents relating to the sale by Sir William Lee of the Fresh Wharf Estate on the River Thames in London.
  - Fresh Wharf Estate papers, 1695-1776; 5 (Box 22)
- Oversize, 1602-1806; Series IX; 8.53; (6 boxes)
  This series contains oversize legal and financial documents, both manuscript and printed, including judgements, contracts, wills, pleadings, and writs.
  - 1602-1704, 12 (Box 23)
  - 1708-1740, 33 (Box 24)
  - 1740-1752, 50 (Box 25)
  - 1753-1789, undated, 30 (Box 26)
  - 1708, 1 (Box 27)
  - 1719-1806, undated, 6 (Box 28)